Finding Aid for the Ward Sykes Allen Family Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Ward Sykes Allen Family Papers
1857-1942
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0023
.42 linear_feet
Biography/History
Ward Sykes Allen, a Nashville native, attended Carson-Newman College in Jefferson City, Tennessee and Vanderbilt University. He received a B.A. in 1947, a M.A. in 1949 and a PhD. in 1963. A relative of Ward Allen, James H. Joyner, was a medical doctor in Sumner County, Tennessee during the late 19th century.
This collection was donated by Ward Sykes Allen.
Scope and Contents
This .42 linear foot collection is comprised of two series. Series I contains correspondence written to Ward Allen from his family and friends during his college years. The correspondence is in the form of letters, postal cards, and greeting cards. This material is arranged alphabetically by first name, with their relationship if known, then by date. Where dates were not included on the letter, the postmark date from the envelope has been used. Series II relates to Dr. James H. Joyner of Sumner County, Tennessee. It contains information on property ownership (tax receipts, insurance policies, mortgage), stock dividend receipts, and lists of medical debts owed to Dr. Joyner for his services (see also, James H. Joyner Collection, MSS #232).
- Correspondence – from Alberta – (2)
  - September 1940 - letter
  - October 11, 1940 – letter
- Correspondence – from Alvin West – (1)
  - September 5, 1940
- Correspondence – from Clare Allen (sister) – (12)
  - August 31, 1940 – letter
  - September 7, 1940 – letter
  - September 23, 1941 – letter
  - October 1, 1940 – letter
  - October 13, 1940 – letter
  - November 2, 1940 – letter
  - November 12, 1940 – letter
  - November 16, 1940 – letter
  - January 25, 1941 – letter
  - March 7, 1941 – letter
  - April 5, 1941 – letter
  - April 14, 1941 – letter
- Correspondence – from Clarence Allen (father) – (8)
  - August 1940 – letter (portion of letter torn off)
  - [September 1940] – letter
  - September 25, 1940 - letter
  - January 29, 1941 - letter
  - February 26, 1941 - letter
  - March 3, 1941 - letter
  - April 10, 1941 - letter
  - May 1, 1941 - letter
- Correspondence – from Mrs. Clarence Allen (mother) – (14)
  - [1940] – letter
  - September 3, 1940 – letter
  - [October 1940] – letter
  - [October 1940] – letter
  - October 29, 1940 – letter
  - November 14, 1940 – letter
  - November 25, 1940 – letter
  - [December 1940] – letter
  - [January 1941] – letter
  - January 24, 1941 – letter
  - [February 1941] – letter
  - [February 1941] – letter
  - March 7, 1941 – letter
  - April 3, 1941 – letter
- Correspondence – from Clifton Allen – (1)
  - September 14, 1940 - letter
- Correspondence – from Dudley Tanner – (3)
  - August 28, 1940 - letter
  - September 23, 1940 - letter
  - n.d. – post card
- Correspondence – from Evelyn – (2)
  - 1940 - letter
  - September 13, 1941 - letter
- Correspondence – from Frank McCullough – (1)
  - September 14, 1940 - letter
- Correspondence – from Henry Miller Cox – (35)
  - August 1940
  - September 4, 1940 - letter
  - September 18, 1940 – post card
  - September 25, 1940 - letter
  - October 26, 1940 – letter
  - November 10, 1940 – letter
  - November 26, 1940 – letter
  - December 1940 – letter
  - January 7, 1941 – letter
  - January 17, 1941 – letter
  - February 9, 1941 – letter
  - February 15, 1941 – letter
  - March 10, 1941 – letter
  - March 26, 1941 – letter
  - April 1941 – letter
  - April 29, 1941 – letter
  - May 31, 1941 – letter
  - June 4, 1941 – post card
  - July 3, 1941 – letter
  - July 29, 1941 – letter
  - August 11, 1941 – letter
  - August 27, 1941 – post card
  - October 10, 1941 – post card
  - October 17, 1941 – letter
  - December 8, 1941 – post card
  - 9 letters – not dated
- Correspondence – from Jane Allen (sister) – (9)
  - August 24, 1940 – letter
  - August 30, 1940 – letter
  - September 2, 1940 – letter
  - September 12, 1940 – letter
  - [1940] - letter
  - January 4, 1941 – letter
  - January 17, 1941 – letter
  - February 3, 1941 – letter [envelope with note attached]
  - March 22, 1942 - letter
- Correspondence – from Jane Allen to Mrs. Clarence Allen – (1)
  - October 1942 - letter
- Correspondence – from Jane S. Huggins – (4)
  - May 22, 1941 – letter
  - June 20, 1941 – postal card
  - September 30, 1941 – letter
  - November 22, 1941 – letter
- Correspondence – from Jeff – (1)
  - n.d. - letter
- Correspondence – from Jenell Greer (cousin) – (2)
  - September 21, 1940 - letter
  - Christmas Card – n.d.
- Correspondence – from Jennie (cousin) – (1)
  - February 1941 - letter
- Correspondence – from Josie G. Ryan (friend)
  - 1940 – letter
  - 1940 – Christmas Card
  - January 22, 1941 – letter
- Correspondence – from Katherine (aunt) – (1)
  - September 17, 1940 - letter
- Correspondence – from Nancy & Dot (cousins) – (1)
  - December 28, 1941 - letter
- Correspondence – from Roberta – (9)
  - August 30, 1940 - letter
  - September 10, 1940 - letter
  - September 11, 1940 - letter
  - October 8, 1940 - letter
  - October 27, 1940 - letter
  - November 16, 1940 - letter
  - February 7, 1941 - letter
  - February 16, 1941 - letter
  - March 2, 1941 - letter
- Correspondence – from Stacy – (1)
  - October 6, 1940 - letter
- Correspondence – from Victor (brother-in-law) – (1)
  - March 13, 1941 - letter
- Correspondence – from William J. Baldridge – (1)
  - October 13, 1940 - letter
- Correspondence – from William Skinner – (5)
  - September 2, 1940 – letter
  - September 12, 1940 – post card
  - October 14, 1940 – post card
  - Graduation Invitation
  - Christmas Card – n.d.
- Greeting Cards – (7)
- Pamphlet – (1)
  - The History of ‘In His Steps’ – by Charles M. Sheldon, 1938
- Photographs – (2)